today we're going to talk about standing
waves
so what exactly are standard waves and
how can they be created
let's say if we have a string
that is attached to two fixed ends
and if we apply
a tension force
and if we pull the string then release
it it's going to create a standard wave
pattern
now there's different types of standard
waves that you can get
you might get a standard wave that looks
like this
you can get a standard wave that looks
now granted because it's vibrating so
fast it might appear to be it might look
something like this
whereas this one
if it's vibrating fast it's going to
look something like
that
now it's called a standing wave because
it appears
not to move
in the
x direction
some waves you can see them moving along
the x direction but the standard wave
it doesn't appear to move because it's
fixed at both ends
thus it's called the standard wave
now let's talk about these shapes
if you have just one standing wave
n is equal to one
if you have a pattern with two standard
waves
n is equal to two
if you get three standard waves
n is equal to three
now each of these standard waves have
the same length
because
if we draw the original picture
the length of the string is fixed
so even though they don't appear to be
the same
the length
is actually the same just keep that in
mind
so
this is equal to the length of the
string o
this is also equal
to the length of the string it's not
drawn to scale
and this is l as well
now
the wavelength
and l is associated with this equation l
is one half the wavelength
this is one full cycle
so basically the length of two standard
waves is equal to one wavelength
so for the second one l
is equal to the wavelength
the subscript corresponds to the n value
it tells you that there's two standard
waves
in that shape
so for the next one
where we have three standard
waves l is going to equal 3 over 2
times the wavelength
so the equation that
relates l and the wavelength is this
equation l is equal to n
times the wavelength divided by two
l
is equal to n
times the wavelength divided by 2.
now if you rearrange the equation
to solve for the wavelength it's going
to be
2 times l divided by n
now all of these standard waves
they occur at the natural frequencies or
at the resonant frequencies
of the string so if you use the
different material that can affect
the standard waves that are produced
now
let's talk about the frequency
let's say that
l is 0.5
and let's say
the frequency for the
the first standard wave pattern
is 100 hertz
this frequency is known as the
fundamental frequency
stand in waves they contain multiple
frequencies
the other frequencies are multiples of
the fundamental frequency
so f2
which corresponds to this particular
standard wave pattern the one that has
two standard waves
this is equal to 200 hertz
this is known as the second harmonic f1
the fundamental frequency is known as
the first harmonic
f3 this is the third harmonic which is
300 hertz
f2 and f3 and anything beyond that
are known as overtones
so as you can see
as the number of standard waves
increases
the frequency increases
so the frequency is proportional to the
n value
the frequency
fn is basically equal to n times f1
we'll talk about how to derive this
equation shortly
now let's talk about the wavelength
as you can see the wavelength is 2l
divided by n
so 2 times 0.5 which is 1
and when n is 1 that's l i mean the
wavelength is going to be 1.
so the wavelength that corresponds to
the first standard wave pattern
in this example is one meter
now what about the next one when we have
two standard waves when n is two
so notice that the frequency increases
with the n value but the wavelength is
going to decrease
because the frequency increased by a
factor of two
the wavelength is going to decrease by a
so originally it was one meter but now
it's going to be
one half of a meter
now what if we triple the end value what
if there's three standard wave patterns
notice that the frequency increased by a
factor of three
so therefore
the wavelength
is going to decrease by a factor of
three so it's going to be one third
of its original value
so lambda three
is going to be one over three
or one third of a meter
so whenever n increases that is the
number of standard waves
the wavelength will decrease
and the frequency will increase
now we said that
the natural frequencies can be found
from this equation it's n times the
fundamental frequency
but let's derive this equation
the velocity of a wave is equal to the
wavelength times the frequency
so if we solve for the frequency
it's the velocity of the wave or the
speed
divided by the wavelength so therefore
fn is equal to
v
divided by
wavelength n i'm going to separate them
into two fractions
so basically all i did was i added a
subscript to this equation
so now we have the equation for the
wavelength we said the wavelength
is equal to 2 times l
divided by n
so then
1 over lambda n
is the reciprocal of this fraction
so that's a n over 2l
so let's replace this expression with n
over 2l
so therefore
fn is equal to
v over 1
times n over 2l
now referring back to this equation
lambda 1 is equal to 2l divided by 1
which is simply 2l
so therefore
we can replace 2l
with lambda 1.
so fn
is equal to
v
times n
divided by lambda 1.
now what can we do at this point
well let's get rid of this first
so as we said before
the wavelength times the frequency is
equal to the speed
and the frequency
is the speed divided by the wavelength
so f n is v divided by lambda n
so f one
if we replace
the n value with one
that's going to be v divided by lambda
one
so we can rewrite this expression as n
times v over lambda 1.
so we have this equation f n is equal to
n
times f1
we can replace this with
f1
so there's a lot of equations that we
can use but let's write down the
important ones let's review it real
quick
so if you know the fundamental frequency
you can find any natural or resonant
frequency using this equation
where n is the number of standard waves
if you know the speed of the wave and
the length of the string
you can find any harmonic using this
equation
so if you want to find the first
harmonic which is the fundamental
frequency
n is one
if you're looking for the second
harmonic which is the first overtone
ns2 the third harmonic or the second
overtone and a string
now we also know that the wave speed is
equal to
the wavelength times the frequency
and if you need to find the wavelength
of any standing wave pattern
it's 2l divided by n
now if you need to find the length of
the string
you can use this equation it's n
times the wavelength divided by 2.
so you need to know how many standing
waves there are and also the wavelength
that corresponds to the standard wave
pattern that you see
now in another video i went over the
wave speed that can be calculated
if you apply a tension force on
a string
the wave speed is equal to the tension
force divided by
the linear density which is the mass per
unit life
and of course the square root of that
result so that's how you can calculate
the wave speed once you have the wave
speed you can find the wavelength for
the frequency
so these are the six main equations that
you need to know
if you know these six equations
you should be fine
now there's one more topic that i need
to discuss before you go into
solving problems
let's say if you have this particular
standard wave pattern
what are the nodes and the antinodes
let's say this is the horizontal line
the
nodes are the locations where the
amplitude is equal to zero
the antinodes
is where maximum displacement occurs
so this is an antinode here we have a
maximum value
here we have a minimum value so that's
also an anti-node
so for standard wave pattern of
let's say
an n value of two where we have two
standard waves
notice that there's three nodes
one two three
and two antinodes
at the anti-node constructive
interference occurs
since we have
the amplitude is at a maximum value
at the node
the amplitude is at its minimum value it
has a value of zero
destructive interference
occurs at the node
so do you need to know all of this for
the test
maybe maybe not
you may be tested on it it may not
happen who knows
but just in case you do see it on a test
you now know what to do how to answer
these questions
so just remember
constructive interference occurs at the
anti-node and destructive interference
occurs at the node
so here's the first question a stanton
wave has five loops
how many nodes and anti-nodes are
present
let's begin by drawing a picture
so that's one
two
three
four
and five
so n is equal to five
now let's count how many nodes are
present one
two
three four
five six
notice that the number of nodes
is always equal to n plus one
so in this case it's six
now how many anti-nodes are there
one
two
three
four
five
there's five anti-nodes
so the number of antinodes
is always equal
to the n value
in this case five so now you know how to
find the number of nodes and antinodes
it's either n or n plus one
here's another one for you
the fundamental frequency of a certain
standard wave is 175 hertz
calculate the first four
harmonics the fundamental frequency is
the first harmonic
which is f1
and that's 175 hertz
now to find the other harmonics
we can use the equation f n
is equal to n times f1
so if we wish to find the second
harmonic it's simply 2 times the
fundamental
or 2 times 175
which
is 350.
so that's the second harmonic
to find the third harmonic
is three times 175
which is 525
and finally
the fourth harmonic or the third
overtone
this is going to be four times 175
and that's 700 hertz
so that is it for this question
now in this problem we're given the
seventh harmonic
use that information how can we find the
fourth harmonic and the knife harmonic
what would you do
now the best thing to do is to use the
seventh harmonic to find the first
harmonic once you have the first one
then you could find any harmonic that
you need
so fn
is equal to n times f1
so the seventh harmonic
is going to be seven times the first
harmonic
f7 is 280 hertz
so if we divide 280 by seven
we can get the first harmonic which is
40.
now that we have the value of the
fundamental frequency
we can find a fourth harmonic which is
just going to be
four times the first harmonic or
four times forty
which is a hundred and sixty
so that's the value of the fourth
harmonic
now to find the knife harmonic
it's simply 9 times f1
which is 9 times 40.
9 times 4 is 36 so 9 times 40 is going
to be 360.
so it's 360 hertz
a two meter string produces a standard
wave with three loops
therefore n
is equal to three
the length of the string is two meters
so what is the wavelength
the wavelength
is basically
the distance of
two loops
now instinctively you can see that the
distance of one loop is going to be two
meters divided by three
or two thirds
so for two loops is going to be four
thirds three loops six thirds which is
two
so you can just look at it and see that
it's going to be
four over three but using the equation
we can get the same answer
and the equation that we need is the
wavelength is equal to 2l divided by n
so this is the wavelength of the third
harmonic so it's two times
l which is two
divided by n which is three so it's four
over three
meters which is one point three meters
now that we have the wavelength what is
the frequency if the speed of the wave
is 45 meters per second
the equation that we need is v is equal
to the wavelength times the frequency
so solving for f
the frequency is the speed divided by
the wavelength
so the speed is 45 and the wavelength is
4 divided by 3.
so 45 divided by
4 3
or 1.333 repeating
is about
33.75 hertz
so that is the frequency
and this frequency corresponds to the
third harmonic
so let's write down what we know
we know the wavelength of the third
harmonic is about 1.333 meters
and the frequency that corresponds
to the third harmonic
is
33.75 hertz
now let's find the fundamental frequency
or the frequency that corresponds to the
first harmonic
so fn is equal to n times f1
therefore f3
is 3 times f1
so 33.75
equals 3 times f1
so we need to divide it by three
so the fundamental frequency
is
11.25
hertz
now what about the fundamental
wavelength
as you mentioned before whenever you
increase the n value
the frequency will increase
but the wavelength is going to decrease
so we can write a similar equation
we can say that
lambda n
is basically lambda 1 divided by n
so to find the first wavelength
or the the wavelength of the first
harmonic
it's n times lambda n
so it's going to be 3 times 1.333
which is a wavelength of 4 meters
now i do want to mention something and
that is the speed is constant you can
find the speed by multiplying lambda 3
times f3
or by multiplying lambda 1
times f1
so if you take a
1.333 and multiply it by
33.75
you're going to get 45 meters per second
and if you multiply 4 times 11.25
you will get the same answer 45 meters
per second
so as n increases
the frequency will increase the
wavelength will decrease
but the speed will remain constant
the wavelength of a standard wave with
one loop is 12 meters
find the wavelength of the first five
harmonics
so let's begin
so the first wavelength
is 12 meters when n is one
and we know
the wavelength in terms of n is going to
be
the fundamental wavelength divided by n
so wavelength 2 is basically 12 divided
by 2
or 6 meters
the wavelength of the third harmonic is
going to be 12 divided by 3
which is 4 meters
the wavelength of the fourth harmonic is
12 divided by 4
which is 3 meters
and the wavelength of the fifth harmonic
is 12 divided by 5 which is
2.4 meters
and that's it for this question
go ahead take a minute pause the video
and try this one
so the wavelength of the fifth harmonic
is 1.8 meters
so lambda 5 is 1.8 m
calculate the wavelength of the knife
harmonic
so we know lambda n is
lambda 1 divided by n
so if we rearrange the equation lambda 1
is
lambda n
times n
so let's find the first wavelength or
the wavelength that corresponds to the
first harmonic
so lambda 1 is going to be lambda 5
times 5
if n is 5. so lambda 1 is going to be
1.8
times 5.
1.8 times 5
is 9.
so the wavelength that corresponds to
the fundamental frequency
is 9 meters
now to find the
wavelength that corresponds to the the
knife harmonic we can use this equation
so lambda 9 is lambda 1 over 9.
so it's 9 meters divided by nine
which is one meter
so that is the wavelength that
corresponds to the knife harmonic
a standing wave with a speed of 30
meters per second
and five loops has a frequency of 250
hertz
what is the length of the string in
centimeters
so let's make a list of what we have
so we have the speed
which is 30 meters per second
and
the standard wave has five loops so n is
equal to five
and we have the frequency which must be
the fifth harmonic
so that's 250 hertz so what equation
should we use to find the length of the
string
well
we can use this one al is equal to n
times lambda divided by two
but before we can use that equation we
need to find a wavelength
so we can use this equation to do that
v is equal to lambda times f
so if we're using the fifth harmonic
then we need to use the wavelength that
corresponds to that as well
so v is 30
the wavelength that corresponds to the
fifth harmonic
we're looking for that
the frequency of the fifth harmonic is
250.
so the wavelength of the fifth harmonic
is going to be 30 divided by 250
which is point 12 meters
so now we can find l
keep in mind n is 5.
so l is going to be 5
times the wavelength
of the fifth harmonic divided by two
so that's five times
point 12 divided by 2
which is about 0.3
meters
now we want the answer in centimeters
0.3 meters
is equal to 30 centimeters if we
multiply by a hundred
so this is the answer for part a
now what about part b
if the string
has a mass of 40 grams what tension
force is required to produce such a
wave now let's keep in mind that the
length of the string
is 0.3 meters
now we know that the wave speed can be
calculated
using this equation it's the square root
of the tension force divided by the
linear density
so let's solve for f in this equation
let's square both sides
so v squared is going to be equal to f
divided by
m divided by l
so let's multiply
both sides by
well first before we multiply both sides
by anything let's multiply this fraction
top and bottom by l
let's rearrange the equation
so these two will cancel
so v squared is equal to f times l
divided by m
now let's multiply both sides by m
so the force times the length is equal
to the mass
times the square of the velocity
so now we can divide both sides by l
so the force is
the linear density mass over length
times v squared
we need to convert the mass in grams to
kilograms
one kilogram is equal to a thousand
grams
so 40 divided by a thousand
is .04 kilograms
so f
is going to be the mass which is 0.04
kilograms
divided by the length
which is
0.3 meters
times the square of the speed
which is 30 meters per second
squared
30 squared is 900 times .04
that's 36 divided by 0.3
is 120 so the tension force that's
required to produce such wave
is 120 newtons
go ahead and pause the video
work on this problem see if you can get
the right answer
and then unpause it when you're ready
so attention force of 300 newtons was
applied to a 0.75 kilogram string
that is 5 meters long
a standard wave with 5 loops was
produced
calculate the speed
so v
is equal to the square root
of f the tension force divided by
the linear density well let's calculate
the linear density first
the mass of the string is 0.75 kilograms
and the length of the string it's 5
meters long
so 0.75
divided by 5
is equal to 0.15
so the linear density is point fifteen
kilograms per meter
so what this means is that
a one meter section of this string has a
mass of point fifteen kilograms
two meters of this material has a mass
of 0.3 kilograms
so 5 meters of the string has a mass of
0.75 kilograms
so now let's plug it into the equation
to find the speed
the tension force is three hundred
and let's divide it by point fifteen
three hundred divided by point fifteen
is two thousand
and the square root of two thousand
is about 44.72
meters per second
so that's the answer to part a
now what about part b
what is the wavelength that corresponds
to this particular standard wave
what equation can we use to find a
wavelength
now keep in mind
since the standard wave has five loops
we have the n value n is five
so we're looking for the wavelength that
corresponds to the fifth harmonic
let's use this equation
lambda n is equal to two l divided by n
the length of the string is 5 meters
long
and n
is also 5 so these two cancel
which means that
lambda 5
is 2 meters
so that is the wavelength that
corresponds to the fifth harmonic
which is the answer to part b
now what about part c
what is the frequency that corresponds
to this stannon wave or what is the
frequency of the fifth harmonic
v is equal to lambda times f
so if we're going to use the
harmonic i mean
the wavelength that corresponds to the
fifth harmonic
we need to use f5 as well
so v is 44.72
the wavelength is two
so therefore the frequency must be 44.72
divided by two
so the frequency of the fifth harmonic
is
22.36 hertz
now what is the fundamental frequency
and the frequency of the first three
overtones
we're going to calculate it using two
methods or two different equations
so we know that fn is equal to n times
f1
so f5 is basically
five times f1
so the fundamental is basically the
fifth harmonic divided by five
so if we take 22.36
and divide by five
we can see that the fundamental
is 4.472 hertz
now if we wish to find the first
overtone which is the second harmonic
it's 4.472 times 2.
which is 8.944
the second overtone which is the third
harmonic that's 4.472 times 3
and that's 13.41
the third overtone or the fourth
harmonic
is four point four seven two times four
now the other equation that we can use
is this one
the frequency of any harmonic is
the speed of the wave times n
divided by two times the length of the
string
we have the speed and the length of the
string so we can use it
so if you want to find the first
harmonic it's going to be the speed
which is
what was the speed again
i may have to recalculate it because i
didn't write it down
speed was 44.72
the end value for the first harmonic is
one
and the length of the string is five
meters so it's 44.72 divided by 10
which
will give us 4.472
now let's say if we want to find
the third overtone
which is the fourth harmonic
it's going to be the speed
44.72
times an end value of 4
divided by 2l
so 44.72
times 4
divided by 10.
which will give you
17.88
so that's another equation that you
could use
if you know the speed and the length of
the string
here's the last question for today the
frequency of the fourth harmonic is 300
hertz
that is f4
is 300
and the wavelength of the second
harmonic is 2.3 meters
so lambda 2 is 2.3
what is the speed of the wave
so notice that we can't use this
equation
because the subscripts don't match they
have to share the same end value
so how can we find the speed of the wave
well something that we can do
is we could find the length
of the string
once we have the length of the string we
can find the speed of the wave using
this equation
so let's calculate the length of the
string
so using this information
n is 2 and lambda 2 is 2.3
divided by 2.
so the length of the string is 2.3
the 2's cancel
so now we could find
the speed
let's rearrange this equation let's
multiply both sides by 2l
so 2l or 2 times 2.3
times f4
is equal to the speed times an n value
of four
these two must match
two times two point three is four point
six
and f four is 300
so the speed
is going to be 4.6
times 300
divided by 4.
so the wave speed is about 345 meters
per second
now is there another way in which we can
get the same answer
it turns out that there is
we can get it by using this equation
however
the subscripts have to match
so we're going to do is find a
wavelength and the frequency that
corresponds to the first harmonic
so fn is equal to n times f1
so f4 is equal to 4 times f1 therefore
is 4 times f1 so f1 is 300 divided by 4
so the fundamental frequency is 75 hertz
lambda n
is lambda 1
divided by n
so lambda n times n
is lambda one which means lambda two
times two is lambda one
so two point three times two
is four point six which is
the wavelength that corresponds to the
first
harmonic
so lambda 1 is 4.6
f1 is 75.
if we multiply
4.6 by 75
we get the same answer
which is 345 meters per second
so that's another way in which you can
calculate the wave speed for this
particular example
so that is it for this video thanks for
watching and i really hope that you
found it to be educational and useful so
make sure you do well on your next exam